<RequirementsAnalysis VERSION="0.3.0">
  <Project>
    <name>@osovv/vv-opencode</name>
    <annotation>Portable OpenCode workflow package with plugins and a Bun CLI for install, sync, and cross-device setup.</annotation>
    <keywords>opencode, plugins, workflow</keywords>
  </Project>

  <Actors>
    <actor-User>Engineer who wants a portable OpenCode workflow across devices and repositories.</actor-User>
    <actor-System>CLI and plugin runtime that install, sync, and execute the configured workflow safely.</actor-System>
  </Actors>

  <UseCases>
    <UC-001>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs `vvoc install` for global or project scope.</Action>
      <Goal>To register `@osovv/vv-opencode` in OpenCode config while keeping vvoc-managed settings in the canonical `$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/vvoc/vvoc.json` file.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Bun and OpenCode are available, and the target config locations are writable.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>The package name appears in the resolved OpenCode config and canonical `vvoc.json` is created under `$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/vvoc/`.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-PLUGIN-INSTALL</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-001>
    <UC-002>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs `vvoc sync` on another machine or after package updates.</Action>
      <Goal>To refresh canonical vvoc-owned config and managed prompt files without reintroducing scattered per-feature config files.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The target OpenCode config and canonical vvoc config can be created or updated.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>The canonical `vvoc.json` file is rewritten canonically and managed prompts are refreshed without requiring legacy config paths.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-CONFIG-SYNC</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-002>
    <UC-003>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Uses `memory_put`, `memory_search`, `memory_get`, `memory_update`, `memory_delete`, or `memory_list` inside OpenCode.</Action>
      <Goal>To persist explicit durable context in the vvoc data root under `$XDG_DATA_HOME/vvoc/`, with `shared` scope visible across projects and local scopes isolated per project.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The package is enabled in OpenCode and memory is not disabled in canonical `vvoc.json`.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Session, branch, and project entries are project-local, shared entries are visible across projects, and stored memory is never silently injected into prompts.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-MEMORY-ACCESS</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-003>
    <UC-004>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Invokes the bundled `memory-reviewer` subagent.</Action>
      <Goal>To audit stored memory and get keep/update/merge/delete suggestions without modifying entries.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The package is enabled in OpenCode and explicit memory exists in scope.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>The reviewer can only read memory tools and returns a report-only audit.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>medium</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-MEMORY-REVIEW</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-004>
  </UseCases>

  <NonGoals>
    <item-1>No automatic memory injection into prompts.</item-1>
    <item-2>No vector store, embeddings, or indexed retrieval in v1 memory.</item-2>
    <item-3>No fallback compatibility with old per-feature vvoc config files once canonical `vvoc.json` is introduced.</item-3>
  </NonGoals>

  <Constraints>
    <constraint-1>OpenCode config integration must follow documented global and project path conventions.</constraint-1>
    <constraint-2>vvoc-managed settings must live in the canonical `$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/vvoc/vvoc.json` file.</constraint-2>
    <constraint-3>Persisted vvoc data must live under `$XDG_DATA_HOME/vvoc/`, not inside the OpenCode config tree.</constraint-3>
    <constraint-4>Config writes must be idempotent and preserve existing JSONC comments in the main OpenCode config where practical.</constraint-4>
    <constraint-5>Memory must stay explicit-only. Stored entries must not be injected into prompts automatically.</constraint-5>
    <constraint-6>Generated canonical vvoc config must be fully seeded and versioned by schema rather than split across multiple CLI-managed files.</constraint-6>
  </Constraints>

  <Risks>
    <risk-1>Repositories or machines may contain stale legacy vvoc config files that must be ignored once canonical `vvoc.json` is introduced.</risk-1>
    <risk-2>Unsafe rewrites of user-maintained config could damage trust in the CLI.</risk-2>
    <risk-3>The file-based memory store performs full scans and may degrade as the number of entries grows.</risk-3>
    <risk-4>Guardian and Memory depend on OpenCode plugin and SDK surface area that may evolve over time.</risk-4>
  </Risks>

  <OpenQuestions>
    <question-1>Should future versions also manage OpenCode skills and agents as installable assets in addition to plugin config and vvoc-owned files?</question-1>
    <question-2>Should memory eventually grow an index or vector-backed search layer once the XDG data-backed store becomes large?</question-2>
  </OpenQuestions>
</RequirementsAnalysis>
