<RequirementsAnalysis VERSION="0.6.0">
  <Project>
    <name>@osovv/vv-opencode</name>
    <annotation>Portable OpenCode workflow package with plugins and a Bun CLI for install, sync, semantic model-role assignment, controller-led workflow routing, and cross-device setup.</annotation>
    <keywords>opencode, plugins, workflow, model-roles</keywords>
  </Project>

  <Actors>
    <actor-User>Engineer who wants a portable OpenCode workflow across devices, providers, and repositories without hardcoding provider-specific model IDs into shared agents or commands.</actor-User>
    <actor-System>CLI and plugin runtime that install, sync, resolve, and execute the configured workflow safely.</actor-System>
  </Actors>

  <UseCases>
    <UC-001>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs `vvoc install` for global or project scope.</Action>
      <Goal>To register `@osovv/vv-opencode` in OpenCode config, seed canonical role assignments in `$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/vvoc/vvoc.json`, set the managed default controller agent, and write shared OpenCode model fields and managed agents to `vv-role:*` references instead of concrete provider-specific model IDs.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Bun and OpenCode are available, and the target config locations are writable.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>The package name appears in the resolved OpenCode config, canonical `vvoc.json` is created under `$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/vvoc/`, built-in roles are fully seeded, OpenCode `default_agent` is `vv-controller`, managed `/vv-plan` and `/vv-review` command definitions exist, and OpenCode model-bearing fields reference `vv-role:*` semantics rather than literal target-specific overrides.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-PLUGIN-INSTALL</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-001>
    <UC-002>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs `vvoc sync` on another machine or after package updates.</Action>
      <Goal>To refresh canonical vvoc-owned config, managed prompt files, built-in role presets, default controller selection, managed command definitions, and managed OpenCode registrations without reintroducing target-based model config or legacy vvoc schema migrations.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The target OpenCode config and canonical vvoc config can be created or updated.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>The canonical `vvoc.json` file is rewritten canonically as the current role-based schema, managed prompts are refreshed, OpenCode `default_agent` remains `vv-controller`, managed `/vv-plan` and `/vv-review` commands are refreshed, and managed OpenCode fields continue to point at `vv-role:*` references.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-CONFIG-SYNC</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-002>
    <UC-005>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Sends chat content or tool payloads that contain secrets while `SecretsRedactionPlugin` is active.</Action>
      <Goal>To prevent raw secrets from being sent to LLM providers while still restoring placeholders where the local runtime needs the original values.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The package is enabled in OpenCode and secrets redaction is not disabled in canonical `vvoc.json`.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Secrets are replaced with placeholders before provider-bound requests, restored after completions and before tool execution, and remain stable across restarts when the configured secret is stable.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-SECRETS-REDACTION</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-005>
    <UC-006>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Starts a primary chat session with vvoc installed.</Action>
      <Goal>To inject reusable main-session guidance such as proactive explore usage without polluting known subagent prompts, including the managed controller primary session.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The package is enabled in OpenCode and a primary agent session is being created.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Eligible primary agents including `vv-controller` receive the reusable guidance exactly once, while known subagents, `vv-analyst`, `vv-architect`, and internal helper agents do not inherit it.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>medium</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-SYSTEM-CONTEXT</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-006>
    <UC-007>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs `vvoc preset list`, `vvoc preset show &lt;name&gt;`, or `vvoc preset &lt;name&gt;`.</Action>
      <Goal>To inspect and apply declarative named role presets stored in canonical `vvoc.json` so that semantic roles like `default`, `smart`, `fast`, and `vision` can be rebound without rewriting OpenCode target fields directly.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The canonical vvoc config exists and contains preset definitions.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>The selected preset resolves by name, only the listed role assignments are changed, unlisted roles are preserved, and OpenCode config remains role-reference based.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-PRESET-SWITCH</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-007>
    <UC-008>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs `vvoc role list`, `vvoc role set &lt;role-id&gt; &lt;provider/model[:variant]&gt;`, or `vvoc role unset &lt;role-id&gt;`.</Action>
      <Goal>To manage the built-in and user-defined semantic roles that shared agents, subagents, and commands can reference with `vv-role:&lt;role-id&gt;`.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The canonical vvoc config exists or can be created.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Built-in roles are always visible, valid custom roles can be added, model selections are normalized consistently, and built-in roles cannot be removed accidentally.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-ROLE-MANAGEMENT</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-008>
    <UC-009>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Uses a shared or project-local OpenCode agent, subagent, or command definition that sets `model: vv-role:&lt;role-id&gt;`.</Action>
      <Goal>To let shared workflow definitions describe semantic model intent while each user resolves those roles into provider-specific concrete models at OpenCode startup time.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The referenced role exists in canonical `vvoc.json` and the package plugin set is active.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Supported OpenCode model-bearing fields resolve `vv-role:*` references to concrete model selections at startup, unresolved roles fail loudly, and role resolution works for both built-in and user-defined roles.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-ROLE-RESOLUTION</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-009>
    <UC-010>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Calls `work_item_open`, `work_item_list`, or `work_item_close` tools during a primary OpenCode session.</Action>
      <Goal>To create, inspect, and close explicit work items that bind every tracked subagent launch to a discrete identity and lifecycle.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The package is enabled in OpenCode and the WorkflowPlugin is active.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Work items are created with idempotent keys, state transitions follow the deterministic workflow state machine, list reflects current state, and close is explicit.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-WORKFLOW-TOOLS</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-010>
    <UC-011>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Launches a tracked subagent (`vv-implementer`, `vv-spec-reviewer`, or `vv-code-reviewer`) through the `task` tool.</Action>
      <Goal>To enforce that every tracked subagent launch carries a valid work-item header, targets an existing open work item, follows the allowed route-specific transition, and does not exceed the review round limit.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The WorkflowPlugin is active and the tracked subagent name is registered in the managed agents list.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Tracked launches without valid `VVOC_WORK_ITEM_ID` are rejected, unknown work items are rejected, invalid route-specific transitions are rejected, review-only fresh work items may start with `vv-spec-reviewer` or `vv-code-reviewer`, and round-limit overflow is rejected. Untracked launches pass through unaffected.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-LAUNCH-ENFORCEMENT</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-011>
    <UC-012>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>A tracked subagent completes and returns output to the main session.</Action>
      <Goal>To parse the strict top-block protocol fields from tracked subagent output, validate work-item identity and status, update workflow state, and halt on protocol errors or hard-stop statuses.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The tracked subagent was launched through a valid work-item identity.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Parsed results update workflow state correctly, `NEEDS_CONTEXT` and `BLOCKED` halt workflow, malformed results fail closed, and counters increment deterministically.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-RESULT-PARSING</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-012>
    <UC-013>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>A tracked subagent review cycle repeats after implementation fixes.</Action>
      <Goal>To cap repeated review churn with explicit counters keyed by work item, blocking round 3 and forcing main-session intervention.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The WorkflowPlugin is active and at least one review cycle has completed for the work item.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Rounds 1 and 2 are allowed, round 3 is rejected with clear next-action guidance, no semantic heuristics are used, and main session can inspect state and recover explicitly.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-LOOP-GATE</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-013>
    <UC-014>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Starts a primary chat session with WorkflowPlugin active.</Action>
      <Goal>To inject workflow protocol guidance into primary sessions so the main session knows how to open work items, use returned headers, treat hard-stop statuses, and avoid free-form review loops.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The package is enabled in OpenCode and a primary agent session is being created.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Eligible orchestrating primary agents including `vv-controller` receive workflow protocol guidance, helper primaries such as `enhancer` and known subagents do not inherit it, and the guidance covers route selection, work-item identity, header usage, hard-stop handling, and state inspection.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>medium</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-WORKFLOW-GUIDANCE</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-014>
  </UseCases>

  <NonGoals>
    <item-3>No backward compatibility or migration path for pre-role vvoc schemas once the role-based schema lands.</item-3>
    <item-4>No target-based model override UX after the role-based cutover.</item-4>
    <item-5>No semantic task grouping or embedding-based work-item identity in workflow v1.</item-5>
    <item-6>No full persistent recovery across process restarts in workflow v1.</item-6>
    <item-7>No workflow tracking for `investigator`, `guardian`, `enhancer`, `vv-analyst`, or `vv-architect` in v1.</item-7>
  </NonGoals>

  <Constraints>
    <constraint-1>OpenCode config integration must follow documented global and project path conventions.</constraint-1>
    <constraint-2>vvoc-managed settings must live in the canonical `$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/vvoc/vvoc.json` file.</constraint-2>
    <constraint-3>Persisted vvoc data must live under `$XDG_DATA_HOME/vvoc/`, not inside the OpenCode config tree.</constraint-3>
    <constraint-4>Config writes must be idempotent and preserve existing JSONC comments in the main OpenCode config where practical.</constraint-4>
    <constraint-6>Generated canonical vvoc config must be fully seeded and versioned by schema rather than split across multiple CLI-managed files.</constraint-6>
    <constraint-7>Semantic role assignments must live in canonical global vvoc config, while OpenCode config stores `vv-role:*` references that are resolved at runtime.</constraint-7>
    <constraint-8>Role resolution must fail loudly for unknown roles rather than silently falling back to a provider default.</constraint-8>
    <constraint-9>Workflow state must be in-memory only in v1. No persistence across process restarts.</constraint-9>
    <constraint-10>Workflow enforcement must use explicit IDs and simple counters only. No semantic clustering, embeddings, n-grams, or fuzzy loop detection.</constraint-10>
    <constraint-11>`NEEDS_CONTEXT` is a hard stop. Main session must gather context before workflow continues.</constraint-11>
    <constraint-12>Tracked subagent names must follow the `vv-*` naming convention: `vv-implementer`, `vv-spec-reviewer`, `vv-code-reviewer`.</constraint-12>
    <constraint-13>Workflow plugin must not pollute untracked subagent prompts or untracked task launches.</constraint-13>
    <constraint-14>`vv-analyst` and `vv-architect` may write durable plan artifacts only under project-local `.vvoc/plans/`.</constraint-14>
    <constraint-15>`vvoc install` and `vvoc sync` treat OpenCode `default_agent`, managed agent definitions, and managed `/vv-plan` plus `/vv-review` command definitions as vvoc-owned.</constraint-15>
  </Constraints>

  <Risks>
    <risk-1>Shared workflows may reference custom roles that are not assigned on another machine, causing startup-time resolution failures.</risk-1>
    <risk-2>Unsafe rewrites of user-maintained config could damage trust in the CLI.</risk-2>
    <risk-4>The plugins depend on OpenCode plugin and SDK surface area that may evolve over time.</risk-4>
    <risk-5>Provider-level alias models such as `openai/vv-gpt-5.4-xhigh` may be required for certain role assignments, so preset usability depends on explicit provider patch setup when those aliases are not native.</risk-5>
    <risk-6>LLM may not reliably follow strict top-block protocol formatting, causing false-positive protocol errors that block legitimate workflow progress.</risk-6>
    <risk-7>Rename of tracked subagents from `implementer/spec-reviewer/code-reviewer` to `vv-implementer/vv-spec-reviewer/vv-code-reviewer` is a breaking change for any external config or prompt overrides that reference the old names.</risk-7>
    <risk-8>In-memory workflow state is lost on process restart, which may confuse users who expect work items to survive across sessions.</risk-8>
    <risk-9>Forcing OpenCode `default_agent` to `vv-controller` during sync may surprise users who intentionally selected another default primary agent.</risk-9>
  </Risks>

  <OpenQuestions>
    <question-1>Should future versions allow optional validation against provider-declared capabilities so that `vision` role assignments can be checked more strictly?</question-1>
    <question-2>Should the role system eventually expose optional diagnostics for discovering which OpenCode config fields currently still contain literal provider/model strings instead of `vv-role:*` references?</question-2>
    <question-3>Should workflow state persist across process restarts in a future version?</question-3>
    <question-4>Should `investigator` become a tracked agent in a future workflow version?</question-4>
  </OpenQuestions>
</RequirementsAnalysis>
