<RequirementsAnalysis VERSION="0.4.0">
  <Project>
    <name>@osovv/vv-opencode</name>
    <annotation>Portable OpenCode workflow package with plugins and a Bun CLI for install, sync, semantic model-role assignment, and cross-device setup.</annotation>
    <keywords>opencode, plugins, workflow, model-roles</keywords>
  </Project>

  <Actors>
    <actor-User>Engineer who wants a portable OpenCode workflow across devices, providers, and repositories without hardcoding provider-specific model IDs into shared agents or commands.</actor-User>
    <actor-System>CLI and plugin runtime that install, sync, resolve, and execute the configured workflow safely.</actor-System>
  </Actors>

  <UseCases>
    <UC-001>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs `vvoc install` for global or project scope.</Action>
      <Goal>To register `@osovv/vv-opencode` in OpenCode config, seed canonical role assignments in `$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/vvoc/vvoc.json`, and write shared OpenCode model fields and managed agents to `vv-role:*` references instead of concrete provider-specific model IDs.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>Bun and OpenCode are available, and the target config locations are writable.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>The package name appears in the resolved OpenCode config, canonical `vvoc.json` is created under `$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/vvoc/`, built-in roles are fully seeded, and OpenCode model-bearing fields reference `vv-role:*` semantics rather than literal target-specific overrides.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-PLUGIN-INSTALL</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-001>
    <UC-002>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs `vvoc sync` on another machine or after package updates.</Action>
      <Goal>To refresh canonical vvoc-owned config, managed prompt files, built-in role presets, and managed OpenCode registrations without reintroducing target-based model config or legacy vvoc schema migrations.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The target OpenCode config and canonical vvoc config can be created or updated.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>The canonical `vvoc.json` file is rewritten canonically as the current role-based schema, managed prompts are refreshed, and managed OpenCode fields continue to point at `vv-role:*` references.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-CONFIG-SYNC</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-002>
    <UC-003>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Uses `memory_put`, `memory_search`, `memory_get`, `memory_update`, `memory_delete`, or `memory_list` inside OpenCode.</Action>
      <Goal>To persist explicit durable context in the vvoc data root under `$XDG_DATA_HOME/vvoc/`, with `shared` scope visible across projects and local scopes isolated per project.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The package is enabled in OpenCode and memory is not disabled in canonical `vvoc.json`.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Session, branch, and project entries are project-local, shared entries are visible across projects, and stored memory is never silently injected into prompts.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-MEMORY-ACCESS</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-003>
    <UC-004>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Invokes the bundled `memory-reviewer` subagent.</Action>
      <Goal>To audit stored memory and get keep/update/merge/delete suggestions without modifying entries.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The package is enabled in OpenCode, explicit memory exists in scope, and the built-in `fast` role resolves to a concrete reviewer-capable model.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>The reviewer can only read memory tools, resolves its runtime model through the built-in role system, and returns a report-only audit.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>medium</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-MEMORY-REVIEW</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-004>
    <UC-005>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Sends chat content or tool payloads that contain secrets while `SecretsRedactionPlugin` is active.</Action>
      <Goal>To prevent raw secrets from being sent to LLM providers while still restoring placeholders where the local runtime needs the original values.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The package is enabled in OpenCode and secrets redaction is not disabled in canonical `vvoc.json`.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Secrets are replaced with placeholders before provider-bound requests, restored after completions and before tool execution, and remain stable across restarts when the configured secret is stable.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-SECRETS-REDACTION</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-005>
    <UC-006>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Starts a primary chat session with vvoc installed.</Action>
      <Goal>To inject reusable main-session guidance such as proactive explore usage without polluting known subagent prompts.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The package is enabled in OpenCode and a primary agent session is being created.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Eligible primary agents receive the reusable guidance exactly once, while known subagents and internal helper agents do not inherit it.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>medium</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-SYSTEM-CONTEXT</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-006>
    <UC-007>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs `vvoc preset list`, `vvoc preset show &lt;name&gt;`, or `vvoc preset &lt;name&gt;`.</Action>
      <Goal>To inspect and apply declarative named role presets stored in canonical `vvoc.json` so that semantic roles like `default`, `smart`, `fast`, and `vision` can be rebound without rewriting OpenCode target fields directly.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The canonical vvoc config exists and contains preset definitions.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>The selected preset resolves by name, only the listed role assignments are changed, unlisted roles are preserved, and OpenCode config remains role-reference based.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-PRESET-SWITCH</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-007>
    <UC-008>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Runs `vvoc role list`, `vvoc role set &lt;role-id&gt; &lt;provider/model[:variant]&gt;`, or `vvoc role unset &lt;role-id&gt;`.</Action>
      <Goal>To manage the built-in and user-defined semantic roles that shared agents, subagents, and commands can reference with `vv-role:&lt;role-id&gt;`.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The canonical vvoc config exists or can be created.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Built-in roles are always visible, valid custom roles can be added, model selections are normalized consistently, and built-in roles cannot be removed accidentally.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-ROLE-MANAGEMENT</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-008>
    <UC-009>
      <Actor>User</Actor>
      <Action>Uses a shared or project-local OpenCode agent, subagent, or command definition that sets `model: vv-role:&lt;role-id&gt;`.</Action>
      <Goal>To let shared workflow definitions describe semantic model intent while each user resolves those roles into provider-specific concrete models at OpenCode startup time.</Goal>
      <Preconditions>The referenced role exists in canonical `vvoc.json` and the package plugin set is active.</Preconditions>
      <AcceptanceCriteria>Supported OpenCode model-bearing fields resolve `vv-role:*` references to concrete model selections at startup, unresolved roles fail loudly, and role resolution works for both built-in and user-defined roles.</AcceptanceCriteria>
      <Priority>high</Priority>
      <RelatedFlows>DF-ROLE-RESOLUTION</RelatedFlows>
    </UC-009>
  </UseCases>

  <NonGoals>
    <item-1>No automatic memory injection into prompts.</item-1>
    <item-2>No vector store, embeddings, or indexed retrieval in v1 memory.</item-2>
    <item-3>No backward compatibility or migration path for pre-role vvoc schemas once the role-based schema lands.</item-3>
    <item-4>No target-based model override UX after the role-based cutover.</item-4>
  </NonGoals>

  <Constraints>
    <constraint-1>OpenCode config integration must follow documented global and project path conventions.</constraint-1>
    <constraint-2>vvoc-managed settings must live in the canonical `$XDG_CONFIG_HOME/vvoc/vvoc.json` file.</constraint-2>
    <constraint-3>Persisted vvoc data must live under `$XDG_DATA_HOME/vvoc/`, not inside the OpenCode config tree.</constraint-3>
    <constraint-4>Config writes must be idempotent and preserve existing JSONC comments in the main OpenCode config where practical.</constraint-4>
    <constraint-5>Memory must stay explicit-only. Stored entries must not be injected into prompts automatically.</constraint-5>
    <constraint-6>Generated canonical vvoc config must be fully seeded and versioned by schema rather than split across multiple CLI-managed files.</constraint-6>
    <constraint-7>Semantic role assignments must live in canonical global vvoc config, while OpenCode config stores `vv-role:*` references that are resolved at runtime.</constraint-7>
    <constraint-8>Role resolution must fail loudly for unknown roles rather than silently falling back to a provider default.</constraint-8>
  </Constraints>

  <Risks>
    <risk-1>Shared workflows may reference custom roles that are not assigned on another machine, causing startup-time resolution failures.</risk-1>
    <risk-2>Unsafe rewrites of user-maintained config could damage trust in the CLI.</risk-2>
    <risk-3>The file-based memory store performs full scans and may degrade as the number of entries grows.</risk-3>
    <risk-4>Guardian and Memory depend on OpenCode plugin and SDK surface area that may evolve over time.</risk-4>
    <risk-5>Provider-level alias models such as `openai/vv-gpt-5.4-xhigh` may be required for certain role assignments, so preset usability depends on explicit provider patch setup when those aliases are not native.</risk-5>
  </Risks>

  <OpenQuestions>
    <question-1>Should future versions allow optional validation against provider-declared capabilities so that `vision` role assignments can be checked more strictly?</question-1>
    <question-2>Should the role system eventually expose optional diagnostics for discovering which OpenCode config fields currently still contain literal provider/model strings instead of `vv-role:*` references?</question-2>
  </OpenQuestions>
</RequirementsAnalysis>
